本字幕由诸神字幕组(kamigamiorg)制作仅供交流学习禁止用于任何商业用途
日听：小伍King翻译：森罗小江校对：Syura时间轴：海底压制：Coolkid
Your face is so freckly, Tadashi!
忠の顔ブツブツ
Why are you so wimpy?
なんでそんなにヒョロちいんだよ
You need to train your body,
体鍛えないとダメなんだからお前カバン係な
so you're in charge of carrying the bags!
Seriously? You're crying?
泣く
He cries over everything!
すぐ泣くよこいつ
Crybaby!
泣き虫
何見てんだよ
Whatcha lookin' at?
Hey, isn't he a sixth grader?
おい六年生じゃねの
ちげよ３組の奴だよ
No, he's in class 3.
That's so lame.
カコ悪
What'd you mean by that?!
何がだよ
Come back here!
おい待てよ
What?
Y-You're lame, Four-eyes!
だダセんだよメガネ
Idiot, idiot, idiot!
H-Hold on a second!
ちょちょと待てよ
"Lame."
「カコ悪」
あの時ツキは俺も含めてそう言たのかもしれないけど
Tsukki might've actually been talking about me too when he said that.
そんなことより
But what mattered more
俺にとての脅威だたいじめ子に対して一人でそれを言えることが
was how he could stand up to the bullies who kept messing with me by himself.
すげカコよくて羨ましかた
I was envious of how cool he seemed.
こんなふうになれたらいいなと思た
I wanted to be like that.
山口は
What about you, Yamaguchi?
What would you say to Tsukishima?
山口なら月島になんて言う
Episode Eight:
Illusionary Hero
I'm heading out.
じゃあお先です
Okay.
Good work!
お疲れ
Hey, Tsukishima!
おい月島
We're gonna practice the synchronized attack, so stick around and help us out for a bit!
シンクロ攻撃の練習すからちょと付き合えよ
I can still go too.
俺もまだいけるよ
There'll be three wing spikers, but that's fine, right?
ウイングスパイカ３枚になちゃうけどいいだろ
俺もタイミング掴んどきたいしさ
I wanna get the timing down.
Wait... You aren't trying to make the roster, are you?
まさかレギュラの座を
Don't think I'm gonna be warming that bench forever.
いつまでもベンチ温めてると思うなよ
Bring it on!
受けてたつぜ
Daichi, let's hurry up and do this.
大地さん早くやりましょう
Let me rest for a bit, man.
ちょと休ませろて
お疲れ
Good job!
Daichi!
大地さんそんな悠長なこと言てらんないんすよ俺
I can't afford to take this lightly!
It's just a high school club.
たかが部活だろ
Miyagi Prefectural Junior High Comprehensive Gymnastics Tournament
Volleyball Match
Left! Left!
レフトレフト
Number four!
４番
あらまた月島君
よしゃ
Wow! It's Tsukishima again!
さすがエスねぇ
That's why he's the ace!
月島ナイスキ
Hey!
Tsukishima, nice spike!
All right!
よしゃ
Amemaru Junior High
Volleyball Team
Where are you gonna go for high school, Big Bro?
兄ちゃん高校はどこにすんの
Karasuno.
烏野最近じゃ白鳥沢に匹敵する強豪だ
They're a powerhouse school that can
compete with the likes of Shiratorizawa.
高校で絶対全国行くぞ
I'm gonna make it to nationals for sure!
I'm home.
ただいま
Welcome back!
おかえり
You stayed late for personal practice again?
また居残り自主練
Everyone's really good, so I can't just sit around.
皆レベル高いから負けてらんねんだよ
Not to mention, Coach Ukai is really strict.
烏養監督厳しいし
But...
I'm aiming to make the roster as a first-year!
目指せ一年でレギュラ入り
There are tons of people on the team, right?
部員の数すごいんでしょ入たらカコいいじゃん
It'd be awesome if you could make the roster.
Right?
Mom!
母さん
Welcome home.
おかえり
Make me three lunches again tomorrow!
明日も弁当３食ね
One for morning practice, one for lunch, and one for before team practice!
朝練後と昼と部活前用
Got it. High in protein and low in fat, right?
ハイ高タンパク＆低脂肪でしょ
Yep! Thanks!
そうそうよろしく
今日肉屋のおばさんに
Today, the butcher lady said, "Your big brother is
on the Karasuno volleyball team? That's incredible!"
「お兄さん烏野のバレ部なんて凄いね」て言われた
You have a match tomorrow, right?
兄ちゃん明日試合でしょ
Can I come watch?
見に行ていい
Hmm...
I'll get nervous if you watch, so nope!
見られると緊張するからダメ
Aw...
Hey, what position do you play now?
ねぇ今てポジションどこ中学と同じ
The same as junior high?
Yeah.
そうだよ
So you're the ace!
じゃあエスだ
Yep!
まあな
What about you, Kei?
蛍はどうなんだよ
You just joined a youth team, right?
この前少年団のチム入たんだろ
I hate receiving.
レシブ嫌いだ
最初は全然思い通りに飛ばねだろ
When you're just starting out,
the ball doesn't go where you want, does it?
Here, get into position.
ちょと構えてみ
Here we go.
行くぞ
蛍
Kei, don't try to push it up with your arms.
腕で上げようとするなよ
こうしかり腰落として全身で送り出す感じにやるんだ
More like this. Lower your hips,
and send it out with your entire body.
Try tossing it to me.
ちょと俺に投げてみ
Wow!
Receiving is where it all begins in volleyball.
レシブは全ての起点だからな
Everything is about keeping the ball in play.
バレは繋ぎが命周りの子たちと仲良くしてるか
Are you getting along with the other kids?
Yeah...
してるし
嘘つけ
Liar!
その顔バレバレだつの
It's written all over your face!
Hello.
こんにちは
Ah! Um...
Thank you for the other day.
この間どうもありがとう
どかで会た
Have we met?
The... other day... a-at the park... The park...
ここ公園で
Oh. So, what are you doing here?
でここで何してんの
Oh, um...
Well, I wanted to play some sport too...
俺もスポツやりたくて
There are a lot of scary guys in baseball and soccer,
野球もサカも怖そうな奴いたけど
but this seemed safe.
ここは大丈夫そうだから
Ah!
Those shoes are awesome!
靴カコいいね
I still only have the school-issued gym shoes.
俺まだ学校の運動靴だから
They're hand-me-downs.
僕もお下がりだよ来週新しいの買うまで兄貴の
I'm using my brother's until I get new ones next week.
Your brother plays volleyball too?
兄ちゃんもバレやてるの
He plays at a real powerhouse high school called Karasuno.
烏野高校ていう強豪でやてる
He's like the ace.
一応エス的な
Th-The ace of a powerhouse?!
きょ強豪のエス
Th-That's so awesome!
かかけぇぇぇ
N-Not really. It's not that big of a deal.
別にそれほどでもないけど中学からそうだし
He was the ace in junior high too.
すげぇぇぇ
Wow!
How long has he been playing?
いつからやてるのこのチムだたの
Did he play on this team?
Aces are so cool!
エスとかカコいい
I'm home.
ただいま
Did your practice match today go well?
今日の練習試合どうだた
Yeah, it went great!
バチリたくさんスパイク決めてきた
I scored a ton!
That's cool.
カコいいじゃん
Let's practice passing.
パス練やろう
After we're done eating.
飯食てからな
Yamaguchi.
山口
次の授業なんだけ
What's the next class?
Japanese!
国語
明日烏野の試合見に行くけど行く
I'm gonna go to Karasuno's match tomorrow. Do you wanna come too?
What, it's Japanese?
My brother keeps telling me not
to come because he gets nervous,
緊張するから来るなとは言われてんだけど
but since my brother's a third-year,
this will be the last match he plays in the prefecture.
兄貴高３だから県内での試合は最後なんだよね
I'll go!
行く明光君の試合初めてだ
I've never seen Akiteru play.
Tsukishima, your brother's on
Karasuno's volleyball team too?
月島の兄ちゃんも烏野バレ部うちもなんだけど
So is mine.
What position does your brother play?
月島んちポジションは
Wing spiker.
ウイングスパイカ
Hey! So does mine.
うちも
選手層厚いから大変だよなぁ
That have a deep roster, so it's always really tough.
If you can't even play in matches, you really have to wonder if going to a powerhouse school is worth it.
試合出らんないなら強豪行くのも考えもんだわ
Tsukki's brother plays in the matches.
ツキの兄ちゃんは出てるよ
What? No way.
俺最近も試合見に行たけど
I saw a match recently, and no one
named Tsukishima was on the roster.
レギュラに月島て名前の人いなかたよ
That's impossible.
そんなわけないだろ
I hear about the matches all the time.
試合の様子とかいつも聞いてるし
You're probably just mistaken.
勘違いじゃないの
You can see for yourself at the match.
見ればわかるだろ
Yeah, I can.
ああ行けばわかる
Miyagi Prefectural
High School
Volleyball Match (Boys)
Miyagi Prefectural
High School
Volleyball Match (Boys)
One more!
Nice receive!
They're going left! Left!
Yes!
That's awesome! Number ten did it again!
ナイスキ
またあの１０番１７０そこそこしかないのに
He's barely 170 cm too!
And he's still a second-year, right?
しかもまだ二年だろ
See?
ほらレフトが三年の川田君と
The guy on the left is Kawada, a third-year,
and the guy on the right is a second-year called the Little Giant!
もう一人は「小さな大エス」て呼ばれてる二年生エスだよ
That's how it's been for a year now!
ここ一年ずと
We get it already!
もうわかたてば
We can see that...
見ればわかるよ
My brother's also a third-year who
hasn't gotten to play in any matches.
俺の兄ちゃんだて三年なのに試合出れてないんだよ
ガツン
Slice.
It wasn't like a movie or drama,
where there are spurts of blood and heads go flying.
ドラマとか映画とかで血が飛び散たり首が吹飛んだりするより
This was far more shocking.
こちの方が断然衝撃的
兄はコトになどいなかた
My brother wasn't on the court.
One more!
一本一本
ナイサ
Give us a good serve!
カコ悪い
How lame.
It was only a high school club,
たかが部活のことだたのに
but for me, that team and volleyball felt like
they were everything my brother stood for.
それを兄の全てであるかのように思てた
In the end, it made him tell pointless lies.
結果兄に不要なうそまでつかせた
So you're the ace!
じゃあエスだ
Yep!
まあな
でも兄も多分信じようとしていた
But he was probably trying to believe in it himself.
頑張ればそうなれると
That if he tried hard enough, it would come true.
でもなたから何だ
But so what if it did?
そんなに必死になるほどのことだたのか
Would it be worth the struggle?
Tsukki!
ツキィィィィ
What?
You've always handled everything in a cool and smart way.
ツキが昔から何でもスマトにカコよくこなして
I was always jealous of you.
俺いつも羨ましかたよ
And?
だから
最近のツキはカコ悪いよ
But lately, you're just lame!
So what if Hinata might become the Little Giant some day?
日向はいつか小さな巨人になるかもしれない
That only means you have to beat him, Tsukki!
だたらツキが日向に勝てばいいじゃないか
You should prove with your skill
that you're better than Hinata is!
日向より凄い選手だて実力で証明すればいいじゃないか
You have the height, brains, and instinct,
身長も頭脳もセンスも持てるくせに
so why did you decide that improving is impossible?!
どうしてこから先は無理て線引いちゃうんだよ
たとえば
Even if I worked really hard and became the best player on the team, what would happen after that?
すごく頑張て烏野で一番の選手になたとして
その後は
Even if we somehow made it to nationals,
what comes next?
万が一にも全国に行くことができたとして
その先は
果てしなく上には上がいる
There's always someone better.
Even if you're able to show some results somewhere,
たとえそこそこの結果を残しても
you'll never actually be number one!
絶対に一番になんかなれない
You're gonna lose eventually!
どこかで負ける
Everyone knows that, so how can they keep going?!
それを分かてるのに皆どんな原動力で動いてんだよ
そんなもん
What the hell do you need besides your own pride?!
プライド以外に何がいるんだ
I never imagined this day would come.
まさか
こんな日が来るとは
When the hell did you get so cool?
お前いつの間にそんなカコいいやつになたの
お前カコいいよ
You're really cool.
Ts-Tsukki? What's wrong?
ツキどうしたの
At the very least, it's better than my worn-out train of thought.
少なくとも
僕がぐだぐだ考えてるよりずと
でも納得はできない
But I'm not convinced by that.
Huh?
I'm gonna go ask something.
ちょと聞いてくる
Tsukki?!
You know, Daichi...
な大地
Yeah?
月島ほといていいのか
You sure it's okay to leave Tsukishima alone?
If we force him to do it, it won't be personal training.
強制的にやらせたら自主練じゃないだろ
I know that, but...
そうだけどさぁ
俺は最初の三対三やた時からそこまで心配してないよ
Ever since that very first three-on-three, I've never been that worried about him.
Though, if Tsukishima starts saying that he wants to quit,
then I'll panic and try to stop him.
でも万一月島がやめるなんて言い出したら
焦て止めるから
そん時は手伝てね
If that happens, I'm trusting you to come help, okay?
月島がどう考えてるか分かんないけどさ
I don't know what's going on inside his head.
俺達はまだ発展途上もいいとこだし
But we're still growing as a team,
and we don't know the limits of our skill.
才能の限界なんて分かんないだろ
もしそれを感じることがあたとしたて
Even if we were to start pressing up against that limit,
we couldn't help but aim for the very top.
それでも上を目指さずにはいられない
Even though there was no rhyme or reason,
we would keep going.
理屈も理由も分かんないけどさ
Indeed.
確かに
!!
Haikyuu
Second Season
!!
Haikyuu
Second Season
First Gymnasium
Yamaguchi said something in a weird voice as he ran off. I wonder if he's okay.
を発しながら走ていたんだけど大丈夫かな
Weird voice?
"Tsukki!" Like that.
ツキて
Oh, so he went to see Tsukishima.
月島んとこ行たのか
何かあたの
Did something happen?
Yeah. He seemed kinda worried about Tsukishima.
なんか月島のこと気にしてた
I see.
月島てさカコ悪いこと絶対やらないじゃん
Tsukishima never does anything that's lame.
He never fails at tests.
テストで失敗とかしないし何でもシャてやるじゃん
He always does things like, "whoosh"!
And "swish"!
シュて
Yeah...
What exactly is the difference
between "whoosh" and "swish"?
シャとシュの違いとは
So I think he'll be okay.
だから大丈夫だと思うんだよね
バレうまいのと下手なの
It's obvious that being good at volleyball is way cooler than sucking at it!
どちがカコいいのかなんて決まてんじゃん
Third Gymnasium
Oh?
What's this?
What do we have here?
There's something I'd like to ask you. May I?
聞きたいことがあるんですがいいですか
Sure!
いいよ
Thank you very much.
すみませんありがとうございます
お二人のチムはそこそこの強豪ですよね
Both of your schools are occasionally considered powerhouses, right?
I guess, yeah.
まあね
Even if you were able to make it to nationals,
actually winning there would be difficult, right?
全国への出場はできたとしても優勝は難しいですよね
But not impossible!
不可能じゃねぇだろ
Now, now, let's hear him out.
まあまあ聞きましょうよ仮定の話でしょ
This is just a hypothetical.
I'm genuinely curious about this.
僕は純粋に疑問なんですが
Why do you try so hard?
どうしてそんなに必死にやるんですか
Volleyball is merely a club, and maybe you'll get to write,
バレはたかが部活で
将来履歴書に「学生時代部活を頑張りました」て
"I worked really hard in my high school club,"
on your resume, right?
書けるぐらいの価値じゃないんですか
"Merely a club"?
ただの部活て
That almost sounds like someone's name.
なんか人の名前ぽいな
Oh, like Merliah Clubb?
タダノブカツくんか
いや待て違ぇよたかが部活だよ
No, wait. I guess it was "merely a club."
Aw, man!
ああそうか人名になんねぇ惜しかたクソ
So it doesn't sound like someone's name. Man, I was so close! Damn it!
Man, it's no good.
突込んだほうがいいですか
Should I say something here?
いいよ切りがないから
What about Justa Clubb?
Nah. There'll be no end to it.
Say, Specky.
ああメガネくんさ
月島です
It's Tsukishima.
Say, Tsukishima!
月島くんさ
Is volleyball fun?
バレボル楽しい
No, not really...
いや特には
それはさ下手くそだからじゃない
Maybe that's because you suck at it?
I'm a third-year, and I've been to nationals.
俺は３年で全国にも行てるし
お前よりうまい断然うまい
I'm better than you. Way better than you!
You don't have to tell me that.
言われなくても分かてます
But I only recently starting thinking that volleyball was fun.
でもバレが楽しいと思うようになたのは最近だ
ストレト打ちが試合で使いものになるようになてから
Ever since my straight spike became usable in matches, I've found it fun.
Straight
もともと得意だたクロス打ちをブロクにガンガン止められて
I've always been good at landing cross-court shots,
but blockers started stopping it.
Cross
I got frustrated and practiced the hell out of straight spikes.
クソ悔しくてストレト練習しまくた
And...
次の大会で同じブロク相手にまたく触らせず
At the next tournament, I didn't let the same blockers touch the ball at all. I hit it right past them.
打ち抜いたた
Just that one spike made me feel like my time had finally come.
その一本で「俺の時代来た」ぐらいの気分だたね
その瞬間があるかないかだ
It's all about whether or not you have a moment like that.
What happens in the future,
if you can win the next match...
将来がどうだとか次の試合で勝てるかどうかとか
None of that matters.
一先ずどうでもいい
Crushing the guy in front of you and the
exhilaration of giving 120% are everything.
目の前のやつぶ潰すことと
自分の力が１２０パセント発揮された時の快感がすべて
Well, that's what's it's like for me.
まあそれはあくまで俺の話だし
It might not fit for anyone and everyone.
誰にだてそれが当てはまるわけじゃねぇだろうよ
I don't really understand why you say it's
"merely a club," but I don't think you're wrong.
お前の言う「たかが部活」てのも俺は分かんねぇけど
間違てはないと思う
ただもしもその瞬間が来たら
But if you ever experience that moment,
それがお前がバレにハマる瞬間だ
that's when you'll be hooked on volleyball.
Okay.
はい質問答えたからブロク跳んでね
I answered your question. Now, help with blocking.
Now, now. Hurry, hurry.
はいはい急いで急いで
ちょああの
Wait, um...
Oh, Yamaguchi came back.
山口くん戻てきた
山口月島は
Yamaguchi, where's Tsukishima?
One more!
もう一本
Let's go!
It looks like he got caught by the
Nekoma and Fukurodani captains.
音駒と梟谷のダブル主将に捕またぽい
何羨ましい
What?! I'm so jealous.
俺も行こうかな
Maybe I'll go too.
Hinata, do you think of Tsukki as your rival?
日向はさツキはライバルだと思う
Huh?
Of course I do!
当たり前だろ
We play the same position,
and he has everything I'm lacking!
同じポジションだし俺にないもん全部持てる
But I'm not gonna lose to him!
絶対負けねぇ
I've gotta practice!
練習
Captain! I'm joining in!
キャプテン俺入ります
If Hinata and Tsukishima are rivals, it's like the Sun versus the Moon.
日向と月島くんがライバルなら太陽VS月だね
Sure.
"Sun" from "Hi" and "Moon" from "Tsuki."
「日」向と「月」島だから
Yeah, you're right!
そかそうだね
Yeah!
しゃあ
I hope that happens.
そうなるといいな
Number four!
４番
Eek...
All right!
よしゃ
That number four is really intense again today.
４番の人今日もすごい迫力
Sir.
先生
Fukurodani                 Karasuno
All right!
しゃあ
Even if you're not able to stop number four's spikes,
at least try to touch the ball.
４番のスパイクは止められなくても手に当てるだけでもいい
Right!
I see.
そか止められなくても手に当てれば勢いが弱くなるてことですか
Even if they aren't able to stop it,
if it hits their hand, the ball loses momentum?
Right.
There are fundamentally two ways of blocking.
ブロクの目的は基本的に２種類で
手に当ててレシブをしやすくするためのソフトブロクと
There's the soft block that's used in order to make the ball easier to receive,
and the kill block that's used to completely shut the ball out.
完全にシャトアウトするためのキルブロクがあるの
Kill? As in, killing something?
キルて殺すのキルですか
Yes.
Eek!
We don't have to stop it?
止めなくてもいいんですか
No.
いいやドシャトできんなら願たり叶たりだ
If you're able to actually shut the ball out,
that'd be perfect.
All right!
よしゃあ
Fukurodani                 Karasuno
Nice receive!
ナイスレシブ俺に寄越せ
Give it to me!
レフトだ４番４番
Left! Number four!
まずは意識しろ
Start by thinking about what you need to do.
Focus your strength in your fingertips so
that they won't be blown away by the ball.
指の先まで力込めろ絶対に吹飛ばされないように
んで手は上じゃなく前に出せ前にだ
And put your hands in front of you, not over your head.
In front.
After that, make this annoying owl shut up!
そんでうるせぇ梟を黙らせろ
Just you try!
やてみろうや
Um... a soft block that reduces the ball's momentum, and...
ええと触てボルの勢いを弱めるためのソフトブロクと
The kind which completely kills the momentum...
スパイクを完全に殺すための
He tipped it!
フェイント
Damn it!
Wow, I thought he was definitely
going to hit it as hard as he could!
今絶対強打で来ると思いましたよ
But it was actually a diversion.
まさかフェイントだたとはさすが全国区エスですね
He truly is a nationals-caliber ace.
大地さん今の
Daichi, did you see that?
Yeah.
Bokuto, you fled from the competition.
木兎さん今逃げましたね
I didn't flee! I avoided the competition!
逃げたんじゃねぇ避けたんだ
上手に避けたの
I skillfully avoided the block!
You got caught off guard.
油断
Oh, fine!
もうはいはいすいませんでした
Yeah, yeah, sorry about that!
Well, now...
いやこれはまた
厄介な雛鳥が殻を破り始めたかな
Perhaps the troublesome baby bird is starting to come out of his shell.
Oh...
The Sun versus the Moon?
太陽VS月
ツキブロク跳んでよ
Come block some balls for us, Tsukki!
その呼び方止めてもらていいですか
Could you please not call me that?
じゃあメガネくん
Then... how about Specky?
All right, let's do this thing, Akaasshi!
よしじゃ始めようかあかし
なんかとばちりが回てきた
Somehow, I got roped into all of this...
Episode Nine:
Vs. "Umbrella"
Next time on Haikyuu!!:
次回ハイキュVS"傘"
"Vs. 'Umbrella.'"